Guide to the Charlotte Phelps Papers, 1955-2013 RL.10178
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charlotte Phelps papers
1955-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Phelps, Charlotte
RL.10178
6.5 Linear Feet 12 boxes
The collection contains the papers of Charlotte DeMonte Phelps, economist and Professor of Economics Emerita at Temple University. The papers are primarily academic in nature, but contain some personal documents. They contain information about her life in academia, course materials, research, and writings. Also present is her professional correspondence.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Biographical note
Charlotte Phelps is a Professor of Economics Emerita at Temple University. She graduated with an A.B. in economics, magna cum laude, in 1955 from Radcliffe College. She completed her Ph.D. in Economics in 1961 at Yale University. She was married to Edmund Phelps in 1957 and subsequently divorced in 1969. She was an instructor at Connecticut College in 1961, and a research assistant with the Cowles Foundation for Economic Research from 1963-1965, before she joined the faculty in the Department of Economics at Temple University in 1967, where she remained until her retirement in 2000. After retiring, Charlotte Phelps devoted herself full-time to research.
Collection Overview
The collection contains several series: Correspondence, Teaching Material, Writings, Professional Service and Personal Files. Most of the collection is comprised of material related to Phelps' academic endeavors. Her correspondence covers 1957-2010 and primarily addresses colleagues across the field of economics. The teaching material is from a number of her most-taught courses and includes student papers Phelps deemed excellent and worthy of saving. The writings include her honor's thesis, dissertation, and a number of published articles. Unpublished works such as conference papers can be found in a compilation of materials prepared for a promotion and tenure committee, along with further correspondence, both of which are housed in the Professional Service Series. Also present are a number of conference programs and proceedings attended by Phelps that attest to her involvement in her field. The personal files deal mainly with her marriage to Edmund Phelps, including a marriage license, photographs, and series of letters following their divorce. Also included are a number of photographs with colleagues and a scrapbook of photographs.
Provenance
The Charlotte Phelps Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2014 and 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual and electronic media is closed to use. Contact Research Services in advance to request the production of use copies.
Women economists -- United States -- History; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher); Economics -- History -- 20th century; Phelps, Charlotte; Phelps, Edmund S.
- Correspondence, 1957-2013; 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This collection contains the correspondence of Charlotte Phelps and is mostly related to her academic endeavors with the occasional more personal note. The correspondence concerns her research and projects, teaching, professional service, requests for copies of her papers, invitations to events, grant applications, and collaboration with colleagues. There are copies of her responses to letters received also included. Arranged by date.
  - 1957 Oct. 16 - 1964 July 28 (Box 1)
  - 1965 Sept. 8 - 1967 Nov. 9 (Box 1)
  - 1968 Jan. 3 - 1969 Dec. 28 (Box 1)
  - 1970 Jan. 9 - 1972 Jan. 31 (Box 1)
  - 1972 Feb. 1 - 1974 Jan. 31 (Box 1)
  - 1975 Jan. 14 - 1979 Nov. 13 (Box 1)
  - 1980 Jan. 8 - 1982 June 17 (Box 1)
  - 1982 July 1 - 1984 Dec. 4 (Box 1)
  - 1985 Jan. 2 - 1986 Dec. 31 (Box 2)
  - 1987 Jan. 16 - 1989 Dec. 27 (Box 2)
  - 1990 Jan. 2 - 1991 Sept. 27 (Box 2)
  - 1992 Jan. 7 - 1994 Nov. 26 (Box 2)
  - 1995 Jan. 5 - 2000 Oct. 25 (Box 2)
  - 2001 Jan. 30 - 2004 Dec. 18 (Box 2)
  - 2005 May 25 - 2010 Feb. 3 (Box 2)
  - 2003 Oct. 5 - 2013 Dec. 19 (Box 10)
  - Ambady, Nalini, 2001-2004 (Box 10)
    Includes correspondence related to research collaboration.
  - Montague, Read, 2008 (Box 10)
    Includes correspondence about sharing datasets and research collaboration.
- Teaching Material, 1973-2000
  This collection consists of teaching material from a number of courses taught by Charlotte Phelps during her time at Temple University. It contains syllabi, exams, course notes and materials, and student papers and exams. Charlotte Phelps noted that she only kept excellent student exams and papers. Arranged by course, then year.
  - Individual Economic Decision Making, 1973-1993; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Social Economics, 1988-1993 (Box 3)
  - Economic Cooperation, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Economic Cooperation, 1994; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Other Courses, 1991-2000 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Student Papers, 1972-1978 (Box 3)
- Writings and Research, 1955-2012
  This collection contains the writings and publications of Charlotte Phelps, including her honors thesis and dissertation. For other writings, see her portfolio submitted for promotion in the Professional Service portion of the collection. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Childhood Antecedents of TAT Motives and Economic Outcomes, 2002 (Box 10)
    Includes drafts and notes for research on the relationship between mother-child interactions during early childhood and economic outcomes in adulthood.
  - Childhood Antecedents of Women's Labor Market Behavior and Earnings, 1997-1999; 2 folders (Box 10)
    Includes drafts and research materials for long-term study on the relationship between mother-child interactions during early childhood and women's economic outcomes in adulthood.
  - A clue to the paradox of happiness, 2001 (Box 4)
    Offprint from the Journal of Economic Behavior & Organization, Vol. 45 (2001) 293-300.
  - The disappearance of polarized altruism, 1991 (Box 4)
    Offprint from the Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization 15 (1991) 91-113.
  - Effects of Mother-Infant Warmth on the Earnings and Family Income of Offspring, 1997-1998 (Box 10)
    Includes drafts, research materials, and grant applications for ressearch project on the relationship between mother-child interaction and adult economic outcomes.
  - Evolution of Caring, 2004-2005 (Box 10)
    Includes notes and correspondence related to republication of article titled The Evolution of Caring in a collected volume.
  - Family Earnings, 2008 (Box 10)
    Includes notes on statistical analyses of determinants of family income.
  - Fertility Regression Printouts, 2005 (Box 10)
    Includes notes and materials for statistical analyses of birth rates.
  - Foraging in the Marriage Market, 2012 (Box 10)
    Includes notes, research materials, and presentation slides for project on personality as a driver of behavior in marriage markets.
  - Gender differences in the long-term economic consequences of parental divorce, 1998 (Box 4)
    Reprinted from the Journal of Economic Behavior & Organization Vol. 37 (1998) 151-168.
  - Intergenerational Transmission of Economic Status and Psychological Well-being, 2008 (Box 10)
    Includes notes and drafts.
  - The Impact of Tightening Credit on Municipal Capital Expenditures in the United States, 1961 (Box 4)
    Bound volume. A dissertation presented to the Faculty of the Graduate School of Yale University in candidacy for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.
  - The Impact of Tightening Credit on Municipal Capital Expenditures in the United States, 1960 (Box 4)
    Published in Yale Economic Essays. Final page states: "This article was prepared in 1960 from a dissertation submitted in 1957 in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy."
  - Is altruism the dominant motivation in the family?, undated (Box 4)
    Offprint from Economic Psychology of the Family
  - Max-Plank Institute Fullbright, 2003-2005 (Box 10)
    Includes materials for Fullbright grant to conduct research at the Max-Planck Institute.
  - Mother's Voice, 1992-2007 and undated; 16 folders (Box 10)
    Includes drafts, notes, grant applications, and related correspondence for project studying the relationships between the warmth of a mother's voice in interactions with offspring during early childhood and offspring's economic outcomes in adulthood.
  - Notes for Case Studies, 2008 (Box 11)
    Includes hand-written notes for case studies on satisfaction.
  - Notes to Relate to Beliefs, Bayesian, 2008 (Box 11)
    Includes hand-written notes.
  - Occupational Choice, 2006 (Box 11)
    Includes drafts and research materials for project on choice of occupation, earnings, and work satisfaction.
  - Preliminary findings from "A Longitudinal Study of the Effects of Mother's Voice on Adult Offspring's Earnings and Family Income", 2001 (Box 4)
    A report prepared by Charlotte Phelps on her usage of a grant from Temple University.
  - Radcliffe Institute, 2005-2006 (Box 11)
    Includes materials for application to Radcliffe Institue Fellowship program.
  - Real and Monetary Determinants of State and Local Highway Investment, 1951-66, 1969 (Box 4)
    Reprint from The American Economic Review, Vol LIX, September, 1969.
  - Reprints Acoustic, 1985-1997; 2 folders (Box 11)
    Includes resources for research on psychological impact of voice affect in interactions.
  - Sears Project, 2005 and undated; 6 folders (Box 11)
    Includes research materials for project investigating relationship between mothers' traits and offspring outcomes in adulthood using dataset on patterns of child rearing compiled by Robert Sears, Eleanor Maccoby, Harry Levin, David McClelland, and Carol Franz.
  - Three Conditions for the Formulation of a Consistent Policy, 1955 (Box 4)
    Reader comments inlaid. Phelps notes: "Paper submitted for honors program. I graduated Magna cum laude. Radcliffe College."
  - Unconscious Motivation and Economic Choice, 1980 (Box 4)
    A Report of a Survey of Temple University Students, 1980, with related findings.
  - Williamson, Cooperation in Hierarchies, 2003 (Box 12)
    Includes drafts and notes for research on cooperative adaptation in hierarchies based on ideas in Oliver Williamson's work.
  - Wives' motives and fertility, 1995 (Box 4)
    Offprint from the Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization, Vol. 27 (1995) 49-67.
  - Writings by Others, 1967-2007; 4 folders (Box 12)
    Includes scholary writings by others used as resources for various research projects.
- Professional Service, 1956-2010
  Included are a collection of documents for Phelps' promotion and tenure, conference documents, and other documents related to her professional service.
  - Documents for Promotion and Tenure, 1966-1999
    - Appendixes 1, 2, and 3 and Unpublished Papers, 1971-1989 (Box 5)
      Appendix 1 contains evidence of research achievement. Appendix 2 is evidence of professional service. Appendix 3 contains evidence of teaching contributions. Each appendix contains an index of contents with further commentary on their relevance. There is also a section of unpublished papers. Bound in a volume sent to the Promotion and Tenure Committee II, Department of Economics, Temple University.
    - Evidence of Achievement, 1972-1974 (Box 5)
      Letters, grant proposals, research and project descriptions.
    - Service Portfolio, 1991-1997 (Box 5)
      Course evaluations, letters, conferences, and other miscellaneous documentation.
    - Proof of Achievement, 1971-1996 (Box 5)
      Newspaper clippings, letters, article reviews, etc.
    - Book, 1980 (Box 5)
      Photocopy of title pages, contents and other relevant portions.
    - Refereed Articles, 1966-1998 (Box 5)
      Includes annotated bibliography of publications. Also includes reprint of article written with Edmund Phelps for The Review of Economics and Statistics in 1966, titled "Factor-Price-Frontier Estimation of a 'Vintage' Production Model of the Postwar United States Nonfarm Business Sector."
    - Unpublished papers, 1976-1999 (Box 5)
      Conference papers and research reports.
    - Other publications, 1980-1999 (Box 5)
      Photocopies of short articles, handbook entries, and other articles.
    - Letters from famous economists: Evidence of professional recognition, 1970-1989 (Box 5)
      Correspondence with renowned economists.
  - Conference Documents, 1994-2010
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Integrating Views on Economic Behavior, 1994 (Box 6)
      IAREP/SABE conference proceedings (Part III).
    - Inquiries into the Nature and Causes of Behavior, 1999; 2 folders (Box 6)
      2 vols. Conference proceedings.
    - Lives in Context: The Study of Human Development, 1999
      Conference documents.
    - Fairness and Cooperation, 2000 (Box 6)
      IAREP/SABE. Conference proceedings.
    - ISNIE Conference Programs, 2002-2004 (Box 7)
      See audiovisual materials for material related to these conferences.
    - Behavioural Economics and Economic Psychology, 2006 (Box 7)
      IAREP/SABE. Program.
    - Behavioural Economics, Economic Psychology: Theory and Policy, 2009 (Box 7)
      IAREP/SABE. Program and abstracts.
    - A boat trip through economic change, 2010; 2 folders (Box 7)
      IAREP/SABE/ICABEEP. Program and proceedings.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1978-1988 (Box 7)
  - Documents from Summer Job at New York Stock Exchange, 1956 (Box 7)
    Research position.
  - Miscellany (Box 7)
    Various clippings, articles, etc. related to Charlotte Phelps' academic service.
  - Yale Club Graduate Fellowship, 2006 (Box 12)
    Includes files related to Phelps's service as a reviewer for the Yale Club of Philadelphia's Graduate Research Fellowship program.
- Personal Files, 1957-2006
  Miscellaneous personal documents.
  - Marriage License, 1957 (Box 7)
    The Marriage Service of Edmund Phelps and Charlotte DeMonte.
  - Proof of Marriage (Box 7)
    Contains engagement announcement, wedding and honeymoon photographs, and various letters from Edmund (Ned) Phelps and addressed to them as a couple.
  - Photographs (Box 7)
    One folder of photographs. Some labeled, some not. Personal and academic photographs.
  - Photographs, 2006 (Box 12)
    Includes photographs from commencement events.
  - Telegrams, 1957 (Box 7)
    Congratulations for election to president of the Graduate Economics Club.
  - Scrapbook, 1986-1990 (Box 8)
    Bound scrapbook containing photographs with handwritten identification. A number of looseleaf items laid in front and back.
- Audiovisual, 1996-2003; 1
  This series contains research data, a pilot for television that Phelps was involved in creating, and conference material. The titles given are from the labels on the items.
  - Prog. #010, Disc 1 - Sides 1 & 2, Disc 2 - Side 1, undated; 1
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0017)
  - Prog. #14, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 8
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0031)
  - Prog. #019, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 2
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0008)
  - Prog. #024, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 3
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0007)
  - Prog. #38, Parts 1,2,3 & 4, undated; 19
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0032)
  - Prog. #048, Disc 1 - Sides 1 & 2, undated; 4
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0016)
  - Prog. #104, Disc 1 - Sides 1 & 2, Disc 2 - Side 1, undated; 5
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0020)
  - Prog. #116, Parts 1,2,3, & 4, undated; 6
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0006)
  - Prog. #120, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 7
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0005)
  - Prog. #148, Parts 1,2 & 3, undated; 9
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0035)
  - Prog. #204, Part 5, undated; 10
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0034)
  - Prog. #204, Parts 1,2,3 & 4, undated; 11
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0033)
  - Prog. #219, Disc 1 - Sides 1 & 2, Disc 2 - Side 1, undated; 12
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0015)
  - Prog. #227, Parts 1,2,3 & 4, undated; 13
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0029)
  - Prog. #227, Parts 5 & 6, undated; 14
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0030)
  - Prog. #229, Discs 1 & 2, undated; 15
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0014)
  - Prog. #234, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 16
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0004)
  - Prog. #307, Part 1 of 2, undated; 17
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0019)
  - Prog. #307, Part 2 of 2, undated; 18
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0038)
  - Prog. #431, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 20
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0003)
  - Prog. #439, Parts 1-4, undated; 21
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0018)
  - Prog. #509, Part 5 of 5, undated; 22
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0037)
  - Prog. #509, Parts 1-4 of 5 parts, undated; 23
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0013)
  - Prog. #610, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 24
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0012)
  - Prog. #616, Parts 1,2,3 & 4, undated; 25
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0026)
  - Prog. #623, Part 5, undated; 26
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0036)
  - Prog. #623, Parts 1,2,3, & 4, undated; 27
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0002)
  - Prog. #632, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 28
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0028)
  - Prog. #633, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 29
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0001)
  - Prog. #643, Parts 1,2,3, & 4, undated; 30
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0027)
  - Prog. #648, Parts 1,2,3,4, & 5, undated; 31
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0021)
  - Prog. #648, Parts 6 & 7, undated; 32
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0022)
  - Prog. #651, Parts 1,2,3 & 4, undated; 33
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0023)
  - Prog. #654, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 34
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0011)
  - Prog. #658, Parts 1,2,3, & 4, undated; 35
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0010)
  - Prog. #670, Parts 1,2, & 3, undated; 36
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0024)
  - Prog. #672, Parts 1,2,3 & 4, undated; 37
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0025)
  - Prog. #683, Parts 1 & 2, undated; 38
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0009)
  - Phelps: Transfers: Tone Disc 2, Tone Disc 3, 1996; 39
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0041)
  - Phelps: Transfers: Tones Side 1, Ref Tone Side 2, 1996; 40
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0040)
  - Phelps: Edits 062596 - Edit Master, undated; 41
    - Digital audio tape original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-DAT-0039)
  - Subjid Sample: Disc 1, Sides 1 & 2, undated; 42
    - Audiocassette original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-CS-0002)
  - Subjid Sample: Disc 2, Sides 1 & 2, undated; 43
    - Audiocassette original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-CS-0003)
  - Subjid Sample: Disc 3, Side 1, undated; 44
    - Audiocassette original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-CS-0004)
  - Filtered excerpts, undated; 45
    - Audiocassette original (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL10178-CS-0001)
  - Women and Work - In the Age of Aguarius [sic - should read Aquarius]. Color 22 min., undated; 46
    Copy of film held in the Schlesinger Library at Harvard.
    Pilot for a proposed television series intended to provide opportunities for women working outside the home to share their work and family experiences with the viewing audience. The series was never produced.
    Guests: Carol M. Huth, Edward J. Huth, Theodora Ooms, Lewis Wechsler. Interviewer: Charlotte D. Phelps. Executive producer and writer, Charlotte D. Phelps; producer-director, David R. Hunt; cinematography, Jeff Hark; editor, Jim Ciarrocchi.
    - VHS videocasstte original (Box 9, Video-cassette RL10178-VHS-0001)
  - Institutions and Economic Performance: 6th Annual Conference (ISNIE), 2002; 47
    See professional service files for conference program.
    - DVD original (Box 9, Video-disc RL10178-DVD-0001)
  - Institutions and Change: 7th Annual Conference (ISNIE), 2003; 48
    - DVD original (Box 9, Video-disc RL10178-DVD-0002)